So now that you've learned to program a microprocessor from the 1970s, I'd like to take a quick fast forward from the 1970s to the present.
Lots changed since the 6502 was available as a $25 microprocessor.
Since the 1970s, there have been about 50 distinct CPU families.
I've been part of this my whole career, lots of research and innovation,
adoption, switching, computer vendors picking one CPU and then switching to another CPU,
generational turnover and overall approach from complex instruction sets to simpler risk instruction sets,
from large refrigerator size mainframes to small microprocessors, then larger microprocessors, faster microprocessors.
Interestingly, after all that, things have settled down in the modern era.
There are two major CPU families in use if you think about consumer and server and desktop.
If you take computers and phones and bring them together, about 90% of the marketplace is ARM-based processors and the remaining 10% is Intel processors.
ARM is very successful because it was focused on low power.
And as computers have gotten faster and faster, we really care more and more about saving power,
both for small handheld devices and for desktops and then even laptops.
And so power savings is really important and ARM was designed to save power.
So let's take a quick case study and look at Apple over the years.
Apple, the Apple I was one of the early adopters of the 6502 in 1997.
And the Apple II and the Apple II and its sort of whole family were a very successful set of microprocessors for a long time.
Apple switched to a different processor, the Motorola 68000 from 1984 to 1994.
During that time, they were playing with a project called the Newton, which was a handheld device, wasn't extremely popular, but it was a handheld device.
Battery powered handheld sort of pocket, but that was using an ARM processor, an ARM processor.
Then they switched from the Motorola to the PowerPC in 1994.
And again, 12 more years they use the PowerPC and then the Intel x86 in 2006, they switched their Macintosh line from using PowerPC to Intel x86.
I was actually in the audience when Steve Jobs announced the switch from PowerPC to Intel x86.
I was amazed, I was sitting, I was working on my laptop, which had a PowerPC in it, had been using it for years.
And at the end, he threw the doors open and we ran into some rooms and there were some prototype Intel x86 Macintoshes running Mac OS.
And it was amazing to me that they could switch from PowerPC to Intel x86.
Then the iPhone came out in 2007 and I was also in the audience when Steve Jobs announced the first iPhone, this iPhone 1.
And I was carrying around at that point in time, I was carrying around a trio as my main computer.
And the trio was one of the things he put up on the screen when he was talking about the iPhone, but the iPhone had an ARM, a Samsung ARM in it.
And so this is an ARM processor. And then in 2020, the ARM came not just to the iPhone, but from the Macintosh.
ARM is not manufactured by one organization. ARM is licensed to many folks to build them.
And Apple builds its own hardware in the Macintosh from 2020 to present.
And what's interesting about that is Apple is currently redesigning their CPUs continuously.
Every year they have a new release. They call it the M1, the M2, the M2 Max, M2 3 Pro or whatever.
And what they're doing is they're actually studying what needs to be in their microprocessor.
And they add instructions to their ARM systems based on what they think we use these for,
whether it's image processing or audio or video gaming or now increasingly artificial intelligence.
And one of Apple's advantages is because they use the ARM and they licensed the core instructions to the ARM,
but then they add their own instructions and then manufacture them.
Another thing about Apple that's kind of interesting is you've been using an emulator,
a code that's written in JavaScript that makes it look like you can run 6502 processors.
Well, in 2005, as Apple was moving from PowerPC to Intel processors, they included a technology called Rosetta 1.
And then when they were moving from Intel to ARM processors in 2020, they included a technology they called Rosetta 2.
And of course, that's a reference to the Rosetta Stone, a famous stone with the connected multiple languages
from sort of antiquity to Latin based languages.
And so what Rosetta did in both cases, it translated the machine code from a previous computer to the modern one.
And the interesting thing was, is it would often run because the modern processors they were choosing,
whether it be the Intel initially or ARM later,
they were so fast that they could emulate the previous generation processors almost at the same speed as the hardware of the previous generation.
And so this really made it a lot easier for those of us who were Apple customers making a transition from architectures,
which otherwise would have almost been impossible to go from one major CPU architecture to another architecture.
So fun aside, there is sort of this indirect connection between the 6502 and the ARM.
And ARM stands for Acorn Risk Microprocessor, and it was built in Cambridge, England by Acorn.
And Acorn originally built a thing called the BBC Micro, which was a 6502 based microcomputer, more popular in the UK.
And so they decided they were going to create a new microprocessor, so they knew a lot about 6502.
The goal was not to make a better 6502, but there was a lot of homage to the 6502 in the ARM.
And so they used BBC Micros to build and simulate the ARM design.
ARM 1 had 25,000 transistors, the 6502 had 4,500 transistors, and the ARM 1 through whatever,
there's many generations of ARMs, and they are the most widely used processors in the world.
And for a good time, you can ask AI to make this historical leap connection between the 6502 ARM and the Raspberry Pi.
And I have a picture of Sophie Wilson, one of the architecture designers of the initial ARM working at Acorn,
working on both the BBC Micro and the building of the ARM microprocessor.
you